Chapter 89. Fast fish and loose fish.
The alusion to the waif and waif poles in the last chapter but one necessitates
some account of the laws and regulations of the whale fishery of which the waif
may be deemed the grand symbol and badge. It frequently happens that when
several ships are cruising in company, a whale may be struck by one vessel, then
escape and be finally killed and captured by another vessel, and herein
are indirectly comprised many minor contingencies, all partaking of this one
grand feature. For example, after a weary and perilous chase and capture of
a whale, the body may get loose from the ship by reason of a violent storm, and
drifting far away to lure, be retaken by a second whaler, who in a calm, snuggly
toes it alongside, without risk of life or line. Thus the most vexacious and
violent disputes would often arise between the fishermen were there not
some written or unwritten universal undisputed law applicable to all cases.
Perhaps the only formal whaling code authorized by legislative enactment was
that of Holland. It was decreed by the states general in AD 1695.
But though no other nation has ever had any written whailing law, yet the
American fishermen have been their own legislators and lawyers in this matter,
they have provided a system which for tur comprehensiveness surpasses
Justinian's pandex and the bylaws of the Chinese society for the suppression of
meddling with other people's business.
Yes, the laws might be engraven on a Queen Anne's farthing or the barb of a
harpoon and worn around the neck. So small are they? One, a fast fish belongs
to the party fast to it. Two, a loose fish is fair game for anybody who can
soonest catch it. But what plays the mischief with this masterly code is the
admirable brevity of it, which necessitates a vast volume of
commentaries to expound it. First, what is a fast fish? Alive or dead, a fish is
technically fast when it is connected with an occupied ship or boat by any
medium at all controllable by the occupant or occupants. A mast and ore, a
9-in cable, a telegraph wire, or a strand of cobweb, it is all the same.
Likewise, a fish is technically fast when it bears a waif or any other
recognized symbol of possession, so long as the party wafing it plainly evinced
their ability at any time to take it alongside, as well as their intention to
do so. These are scientific commentaries, but the commentaries of
the whalemen themselves sometimes consist in hard words and harder knocks,
the eco upon little of the fist. True, among the more upright and honorable
whalemen, allowances are always made for particular cases where it would be an
outrageous moral injustice for one party to claim possession of a whale
previously chased or killed by another party, but others are by no means so scrupulous.
Some 50 years ago, there was a curious case of a whale trover litigated in
England, wherein the plaintiffs set forth that after a hard chase of a whale
in the northern seas, and when indeed they, the plaintiffs, had succeeded in
harpooning the fish, they were at last, through peril of their lives, obliged to
forsake not only their lines, but their boat itself. Ultimately, the defendants,
the crew of another ship, came up with the whale, struck, killed, seized, and
finally appropriated it before the very eyes of the plaintiffs. And when those
defendants were remmonstrated with, their captain snapped his fingers in the
plaintiff's teeth, and assured them that by way of doxology to the deed he had
done, he would now retain their line, harpoons, and boat, which had remained
attached to the whale at the time of the seizure. Wherefore the plaintiffs now
sued for the recovery of the value of their whale, line, harpoons, and boat.
Mr. Erskin was counsel for the defendants. Lord Ellenboroough was the
judge. In the course of the defense, the witty Erskin went on to illustrate his
position by alluding to a recent Crim Khan case, wherein a gentleman, after in
vain trying to bridle his wife's viciousness, had at last abandoned her
upon the seas of life, but in the course of years repenting of that step, he
instituted an action to recover possession of her. Erskin was on the
other side, and he then supported it by saying that though the gentleman had
originally harpooned the lady, and had once had her fast, and only by reason of
the great stress of her plunging viciousness, had at last abandoned her,
yet abandoned her he did, so that she became a loose fish. And therefore, when
a subsequent gentleman re-harped her, the lady then became that subsequent
gentleman's property, along with whatever harpoon might have been found sticking in her.
Now, in the present case, Erskin contended that the examples of the whale
and the lady were reciprocally illustrative of each other.
These pleadings and the counter pleadings being duly heard, the very
learned judge in set terms decided to wit, that as for the boat, he awarded it
to the plaintiffs because they had merely abandoned it to save their lives,
but that with regard to the controverted whale, harpoons and line, they belonged
to the defendants. the whale because it was a loose fish at the time of the
final capture and the harpoons in line because when the fish made off with them
it the fish acquired a property in those articles and hence anybody who
afterwards took the fish had a right to them. Now the defendants afterwards took
the fish ergo the four said articles were theirs.
A common man looking at this decision of the very learned judge might possibly
object to it. But plowed up to the primary rock of the matter, the two
great principles laid down in the twin whailing laws previously quoted and
applied and elucidated by Lord Ellenboroough in the above case. These
two laws touching fast fish and loose fish, I say, will on reflection be found
the fundamentals of all human juristprudence. For notwithstanding its
complicated tracery of sculpture, the temple of the law, like the temple of
the Philistines, has but two props to stand on.
Is it not a saying in everyone's mouth, possession is half of the law? That is,
regardless of how the thing came into possession, but often possession is the
whole of the law. What are the senus and souls of Russian surfs and republican
slaves but fast fish? Whereof possession is the whole of the law? What to the
rapacious landlord is the widow's last might but a fast fish. What is yonder
undetected villain's marble mansion with a door plate for a waif? What is that
but a fast fish? What is the ruinous discount which Morai the broker gets
from poor Wobiggon the bankrupt on a loan to keep Wobiggon's family from
starvation? What is that ruinous discount but a fast fish? What is the
archbishop of save souls income of 100,000 seized from the scant bread and cheese
of hundreds of thousands of brokenbacked laborers all sure of heaven without any
of save souls help? What is that globular 100,000 pounds but a fast fish?
What are the Duke of Dunders hereditary towns and hamlets but fast fish? What to
that redoubted harpooner John Bull is poor Ireland but a fast fish? What to
that apostolic lancer brother Jonathan is Texas but a fast fish? And concerning
all these is not possession the whole of the law. But if the doctrine of fast
fish be pretty generally applicable, the kindred doctrine of loose fish is still
more widely so that is internationally and universally applicable. What was
America in 1492, but a loose fish in which Columbus struck the Spanish
standard by way of wafing it for his royal master and mistress? What was
Poland to thesar? What Greece to the Turk? What India to England? What at
last will Mexico be to the United States? All loose fish. What are the
rights of man and the liberties of the world but loose fish? What all men's
minds and opinions but loose fish? What is the principle of religious belief in
them but a loose fish? What to the ostentatious smuggling verbalists are
the thoughts of thinkers but loose fish?
What is the great globe itself but a loose fish? And what are you reader but
a loose fish and a fast fish too?